A Finding Aid to the Reginald Marsh Papers, 1897-1955, in the Archives of American Art AAA.marsregi
Archives of American Art
Reginald Marsh papers
1897-1955
AAA.marsregi
Archives of American Art
8.5 Linear feet
The papers of Reginald Marsh (1898-1954) measure approximately 8.5 linear feet and date from circa 1897 to 1955. The collection documents the life and work of the artist, who was best known for his paintings and illustrations depicting scenes of vaudeville, night clubs, burlesque, and New York City. Marsh was a lifelong free-lance illustrator for the New Yorker, Esquire and many other national magazines. Papers include correspondence, diaries, notebooks, sketches, scrapbooks, business and financial papers, and photographs, as well as some biographical and printed material.
Marsh, Reginald
Provenance
A large portion of the Reginald Marsh papers, including diaries, notebooks, sketchbooks, and photograph albums, was lent for microfilming in 1963 by Marsh's wife, Felicia Meyer Marsh. Some, but not all, of this material was subsequently donated to AAA in 1979, after the death of Mrs. Marsh, along with some additional material, including notebooks, scrapbooks, biographical and printed material. Another portion of the collection, comprised mainly of correspondence and a catalog of Marsh's art work, was donated in 1964. Three items of Marsh juvenilia were donated in 1984 by Alice Heffernan. Sketches that Mrs. Marsh bequeathed to the Whitney Museum were donated to AAA by the museum in 1987, along with 5 sketchbooks previously lent. Later gift portions were microfilmed.
Separated Material
Some of the material loaned for microfilming in 1963, including the bulk of Marsh's sketchbooks and some anatomy sketches, was subsequently donated to the Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York Public Library, and Whitney Museum of American Art. Other loaned material, including several small paintings, was from the Pierpont Morgan Library. Most of the files of clippings that were donated to AAA with Marsh's papers were transferred to the Smithsonian American Art Museum and National Portrait Gallery Library in 1979. Even though this material is not technically part of the collection housed in AAA, copies are available on microfilm reels NRM3-NRM17 (sketchbooks and sketches), NRM 19 (material from the Pierpont Morgan Library), NRM 20 (small paintings), and 2233-2234 (clippings). A portion of the material donated to AAA with the Reginald Marsh papers has been separated to create a new collection of Felicia Meyer Marsh and Marsh Family papers. Loaned and transferred material is not described in this finding aid.
Related Material
The Archives holds several collections of different provenance that relate to Reginald Marsh, including Felicia Meyer Marsh and Meyer Family Papers (available on reels 2082, 2087-2090, and 4474-4475), Fred Dana Marsh illustrated letters (available on reel 3134), Norman Sasowsky Research Material on Reginald Marsh (partially available on reels 1195 and 1463-1464), and Reginald Marsh Printed Material, consisting of two yearbooks from Lawrenceville School donated by Alvin Macauley who was a classmate of Marsh (not available on microfilm). In addition, a portion of the materials loaned and microfilmed in 1963 on reel NRM 19, including several small paintings, are housed in the Pierpont Morgan Library.
Restrictions on Access
The bulk of the collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website. Use of material not digitized requires an appointment.
Alternative Forms Available
The papers of Reginald Marsh were scanned by the Archives of American Art in 2006, and total 9242 images.
Items that typically have not been digitized include typescript copies of published art catalogs that are widely available elsewhere, transparencies, miscellaneous photographs of works of art, scattered clippings and printed material, and any duplicated material.
Biographical Note
Reginald Marsh was born in Paris on March 14, 1898. His father, Fred Dana Marsh, was a well-known muralist, and his mother, Alice Randall Marsh, was also an artist who painted miniature watercolors. Marsh returned with his family to the United States in 1900 and grew up in Nutley, New Jersey.
After graduating from Yale University in 1920, Marsh moved to New York, where he worked as an illustrator for the New York Evening Post and Herald, Vanity Fair and Harper's Bazaar. Beginning in 1922, he worked as staff artist at the New York Daily News doing a cartoon review of vaudeville and burlesque. During the 1920s, he designed theater curtains for the Greenwich Village Follies and other theater productions, and became one of the original cartoonists at The New Yorker after it was founded in 1925, actively working for the magazine until 1931 and regularly contributing drawings from time to time after that.
In 1923, Marsh married Betty Burroughs, who was the daughter of the curator of painting at the Metropolitan Museum of Art and herself a sculptor. They divorced in 1933, and he married his second wife, Felicia Meyer, a landscape painter, in 1934.
In the early 1920s, Marsh began to study painting and attended classes taught by John Sloan and Kenneth Hayes Miller, among others, at the Art Students League in New York. He made several trips to Europe, once in 1925-1926 and again in 1928, to study the old masters in the museums. In 1929, he began to paint in egg tempera. He also worked in watercolor, painting several large compositions in 1939-1940. In the 1940s, he studied the "Maroger medium" with Jacques Maroger and began to use this emulsion technique in his paintings. In addition to painting, he also worked in lithography, etching, and engraving.
Marsh had his first one-man show of oils and watercolors at the Whitney Studio Club in 1924 and another show of lithographs there in 1928. He had one-man shows of his watercolors at the Valentine Dudensing Galleries in 1927, the Weyhe Gallery in 1928, and the Marie Sterner Galleries in 1929. In 1930, he had his first show of paintings at the Rehn Galleries, where he regularly exhibited for the next two decades.
In 1935 and 1937 respectively, Marsh was commissioned by the Treasury Department Art Program to paint two murals in the Post Office Department Building in Washington, D.C. and a series of murals in the rotunda of the Customs House in New York. Beginning in 1935, Marsh taught drawing and painting at the Art Students League. In the summer of 1946, he was guest instructor at Mills College, Oakland, California, for six weeks. In 1949, he was appointed head of the Department of Paintings at Moore Institute of Art, Science, and Industry, Philadelphia and taught advanced painting there in 1953-1954.
Beginning in the mid-1930s, some of Marsh's art work began to be reproduced on greeting cards issued by the American Artists Group and Living American Art, Inc. He also did illustrations for editions of Theodore Dreiser's Sister Carrie (1938), John Dos Passos's USA (1945) and Adventures of a Young Man (1946), and Mark Twain's The Prince and the Pauper (1946), among others. He continued to do freelance illustrations for magazines, including Esquire, Fortune, and Life. Notably, he served as an artist correspondent for Life during the Second World War, and traveled to Brazil in 1943 to draw the army installations there.
Marsh was the recipient of various awards throughout his career, including the M. V. Kohnstamm Prize from the Art Institute of Chicago in 1931, the First W. A. Clark Prize and Corcoran Gold Medal from the Corcoran Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C., in 1945, and the Gold Medal for Graphic Arts of the National Institute of Arts and Letters in 1954.
Marsh died of a heart attack in Dorset, Vermont on July 3, 1954.
This biographical note draws heavily from information originally printed in the catalogue of the Reginald Marsh Retrospective Exhibition organized by the Whitney Museum in 1955.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Reginald Marsh (1898-1954) measure approximately 8.5 linear feet and date from circa 1897 to 1955. The collection documents the life and work of the artist, who was best known for his paintings and illustrations depicting scenes of vaudeville, night clubs, burlesque, and New York City. Marsh was a lifelong free-lance illustrator for the New Yorker, Esquire and many other national magazines. Papers include correspondence, diaries, notebooks, sketches, scrapbooks, business and financial papers, and photographs, as well as some biographical and printed material.
Marsh's correspondence is typically with family, friends, artists, colleagues, dealers, government officials, publishers, greeting card companies, admirers and former students. Correspondence concerns both personal and professional matters, documenting his relationships with family and friends and his work on various projects ranging from book illustrations to the murals he executed as part of the Treasury Department Art Program. Diaries include those Marsh kept as an adolescent, those in which he recorded his technique and work on art, and those in which he recorded his daily engagements. Notebooks include ones on art, in which he recorded notes on particular works and on painting techniques, mediums and other processes; ones used as address books and to record notes on travel and art work; and ones on finances, in which he kept track of earnings from his stocks and art, as well as some student notebooks. Diaries and notebooks both document various practical aspects involved in the creation of Marsh's art work.
Sketches include ones on loose sheets and scraps of paper and in sketchbooks, documenting some of the sources and recurrent themes of Marsh's art work, as well as shedding light on Marsh's process of creation. Scrapbooks consist primarily of clippings (illustrations, reviews, reproductions of art work) compiled by Marsh, documenting the publication, exhibition, and reception of his art work. Business and financial papers consist of paperwork (contracts, agreements, statements, receipts, permissions) relating to business matters, practical concerns, and financial aspects involved in handling his various art projects and in exhibiting and selling his art work. Photographs include ones of Marsh's family and friends, the artist at work (sketching around Coney Island and on the streets of New York), and his art work (some of which was compiled into volumes by Marsh and some of which was compiled by Norman Sasowsky).
Also found are limited amounts of biographical material, including juvenilia, official documents, awards and certificates, writings, an appraisal of Marsh's estate, and catalogs of Marsh's art work, and printed material, including exhibition catalogs, clippings, and publications.
Arrangement
The Reginald Marsh papers are arranged as 9 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1910s-1955 (boxes 1, 11; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1920-1954 (boxes 1-2, OV 12; 1.2 linear feet)
Series 3: Diaries, 1912-1954 (box 3; 1 linear foot)
Series 4: Notebooks, 1919-1954 (box 4; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 5: Sketches, 1901-1954, undated (boxes 4-5, OV 12-21; 1.4 linear feet)
Series 6: Scrapbooks, 1901-1954, undated (boxes 6, 9-11; 1.5 linear feet)
Series 7: Business and Financial Papers, 1923-1954 (box 6; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 8: Photographs, circa 1897-1908, 1920-1952 (boxes 6-8, 10; 1.3 linear feet)
Series 9: Printed Material, 1931-1955 (boxes 8, 10; 0.2 linear feet)
Benton, William, 1900-1973; Kuniyoshi, Yasuo, 1889-1953; Marsh, Felicia Meyer, 1912 or 3-1978; Marsh, Fred Dana, 1872-1961; Powys, Llewelyn, 1884-1939; Shubert, Katherine Schmidt, 1898-1978; Woodhouse, Betty Burroughs, 1899-; Art--Philosophy; Diaries; Etchers--New York (State)--New York; Illustrators--New York (State)--New York; Muralists--New York (State)--New York; Painters--New York (State)--New York; Painting, American; Painting--Technique; Photographs; Sketchbooks
- Biographical Material, circa 1910s-1955, undated; Series 1; (boxes 1, 11; 0.8 linear feet)
  Scope and Contents note
  Series consists of some Marsh juvenilia, official documents (including a French identity card, a union card, and various customs and pier passes), awards and certificates, writings by and about Marsh, greeting cards featuring reproductions of art work by Marsh, and ephemera. Juvenilia includes a letter from Marsh to his mother, a sketch of Marsh as young boy (presumably by his mother), and a booklet of poems by Marsh (a copy can also be found amongst his scrapbooks). Writings by Marsh include some notes and a final copy of the speech he gave at the American Artists' Congress Symposium held at the Museum of Modern Art in 1940. Also included are typescript copies of the multi-volume catalog of Marsh's art work by Norman Sasowsky.
  - Juvelinia, 1910s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Official Documents, 1928-1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Awards and Certificates, 1937-1943; (See also Box 11) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Writings (Box 1)
    - Speech by Marsh Given at American Artists' Congress Symposium, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Speech Given by Isabel Bishop Upon the Presention to Marsh of the Gold Medal for Graphic Arts, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Student Paper on Marsh by Elizabeth S--, undated; (Not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Greeting Cards Featuring Art Work by Marsh, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous, 1953, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Wallet, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Parts of Envelopes with Identifying Information about Prints, undated; (4 folders; not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 10-13)
  - Appraisal of Marsh Estate, 1955; (Not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Catalog of Marsh's Art Work by Norman Sasowsky (Box 1)
    - Volume I, undated; (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
    - Volume II, undated; (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
    - Volume III, undated; (3 folders; not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
  - Catalog of Marsh's Watercolors (incomplete), undated; (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Oversize, Awards and Certificates, 1937-1943; (See Box 1, F3) (Box 11 (sol))
- Correspondence, 1920-1954; Series 2; (boxes 1-2, OV 12; 1.2 linear feet)
  Series consists of Marsh's personal and professional correspondence. Among the correspondents are vaudeville performers and producers, artists, museums, galleries, publishers, greeting card companies, government officials, admirers, and former students, as well as family and friends. Correspondence largely concerns Marsh's career as a painter and illustrator, and his relationships with family, friends, and colleagues.
  Correspondence documents his work as a vaudeville reviewer for the New York Daily News from 1922 to 1925; the sale and exhibition of his art work; the publication of his illustrations and caricatures in various magazines; his book illustrations; and the reproduction of his art work on greeting cards produced by American Artists Group and Living American Art, Inc. There are also extensive files (which also contain scattered business, financial, and travel documents) relating to his work on two federal art projects, murals in the Post Office Department, Washington, D.C. (1935) and the Customs House in New York (1937), and his assignment as an artist correspondent in Brazil during the Second World War (1943). Similar materials are also found amongst the business and financial papers in Series 7.
  Correspondence documents his relationships with his father, Fred Dana Marsh, his first wife, Betty Burroughs, and his second wife, Felicia Meyer Marsh, as well as his relationships with friends and colleagues, including the English writer, Llewelyn Powys, the artists, Yasuo and Katherine Kuniyoshi, and the U.S. Senator (and former Yale classmate), William Benton, who ended up being one of the largest collectors of Marsh's work.
  Letters from artists, such as Edward Laning, and curators, such as Lloyd Goodrich, provide some sense of Marsh's methods and techniques for creating art work (especially his use of the "Maroger medium") and his views on art and current art movements (especially Abstract Expressionism). Correspondence pertaining to the award competition for the U.S. Building at the New York World's Fair, which includes versions of Marsh's letters to and letters from Edward Bruce of the Treasury Department Section of Painting and Sculpture, is especially suggestive of Marsh's strong feelings of "despair" over the lack of originality in contemporary art.
  General correspondence is typically arranged in chronological files, interspersed with files named according to correspondent. Letters are typically to Marsh, unless otherwise noted. Project correspondence is arranged according to the name of the project on which Marsh worked or to which correspondence pertains. Envelopes, which had at some earlier point been separated from correspondence, and greeting cards are arranged in files at the end of the series. An appendix of significant correspondent's names from the chronological files is included in this finding aid.
  See index for a list of selected correspondents from Series 2. The list does not include names of family.
  Index: Selected Correspondents from Series 2
  This list represents only a selection of correspondents and does not include names of family.
  General Correspondence
  American Artists Group, Inc.: 1935, 1936, 1937, 1938, 1941, 1942
  Archer, Edmund: 1944, 1949
  Arms, John Taylor: 1945, 1948, 1951
  Art Institute of Chicago (School): 1945
  Arts Bureau of Gartner and Bender, Inc.: 1947
  Associated American Artists, Inc.: 1940
  Barrymore, Lionel: 1949
  Bartlett, Clay: 1948, 1949, 1950, 1951, 1952, undated
  Baum, Richard F.: 1953, 1954
  Bishop, Isabel: 1942, 1950, undated
  Book-of-the-Month Club: 1945, 1946
  Bork, Jacob: 1936
  Burroughs, Alan: 1930, 1953
  Carnegie Institute: 1947
  Coates, Robert M.: 1921, 1922, 1954, undated
  Corcoran Gallery of Art: 1945, 1954
  Cornelius, Marty: 1948, 1949, 1950, 1952
  Coutts, Jeane: 1946, 1948, 1949, 1950, 1951
  Dreiser, Theodore: 1939
  Eakins, Susan: 1928, 1929
  Genauer, Emily: 1952
  Goodrich, Lloyd: 1927, 1940, 1951, undated
  Gregory, Alyse: 1936, 1938, 1940, 1945, 1947, 1952, 1953
  Hallmark Cards (Hall Brothers Inc.): 1950, 1951
  Harper's Magazine: 1953
  Hartmann, Sadakichi: 1939
  Hopkins, Peter: 1951
  Houghton Miflin Company: 1946, 1947, 1948, 1949, 1950, 1954
  Huntley, Victoria Hutson: 1948
  Kelly, Augustus: 1942, 1943, 1944
  Kinsey, Alfred C.: 1950
  Kuniyoshi, Katherine (Schmidt): 1922, 1926, 1927, 1928, 1929, 1930, 1932, 1933, undated
  Kuniyoshi, Yasuo: 1922, 1928, 1929, 1930, 1931, undated
  Laning, Edward: 1943, 1948, 1949, 1950, 1951, 1952
  Larkin, Oliver: 1951
  Life Magazine: 1943
  Limited Editions Club: 1953, 1954
  Living American Art, Inc.: 1936, 1937, 1938, 1940, 1941
  Mandel, Estelle: 1951
  Maroger, Jacques: 1942, 1943, 1944, 1945, 1948, 1950, 1951, 1952, 1953, undated
  Merton, Owen: 1927, 1928
  Merton, Thomas: 1932, undated
  Metropolitan Museum of Art: 1951, 1954
  Museum of the City of New York: 1953, 1954
  Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, Massachusetts: 1942
  Miller, Kenneth Hayes: 1929, 1933, 1943
  National Academy of Design: 1944
  National Institute of Arts and Letters: 1954
  New York Times: 1942
  Nordmark, Olle: 1939
  Overton, Richard C.: 1951, 1952, 1954
  Pantheon Books Inc.: 1951, 1954
  Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts: 1941
  Philadelphia Museum of Art: 1944
  Pierpont Morgan Library: 1951
  Powys, Llewelyn: 1927, 1929, 1930, 1931, 1932, 1933, 1934, 1936, 1937, 1938, 1939, undated
  Pratt Institute: 1949
  Redelius, Frank: 1952, 1953
  Rehn Galleries (Frank K. M. Rehn, Inc.): 1948
  Rose, Billy: 1950
  Rothschild, Lincoln: 1950
  Royal Society of Arts, London: 1947
  Soyer, Raphael: 1951
  Treasury Department, Washington: 1944, 1952
  University of Rochester, College of Arts and Sciences: 1940
  Weyhe Gallery (E. Weyhe): 1943
  Whitney Museum of American Art: 1944, 1953, 1954
  Wilder, Thornton: 1923
  Worcester Art Museum: 1951
  Wyeth, Andrew: 1952, 1953
  Project Correspondence
  Biddle, George: 1935, 1943
  Bruce, Edward: 1938
  Dows, Olin: 1935, 1936
  Jones, Cecil H.: 1936, 1937, 1938
  Nordmark, Olle: 1935, 1936, 1937, 1941, 1942
  Owen, William B.: 1936
  Rowan, Edward B.: 1935, 1936
  Sharkey, Alice M.: 1936
  Watson, Forbes: 1936, 1937
  - General Correspondence (Box 1)
    - 1920-1922 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - 1923 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - 1924-1925 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - 1926-1928 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - General Correspondence (Box 2)
    - 1938-1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1943 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1944-1945 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1946-1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1948 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1949 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1950 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1951, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
    - 1952, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
    - 1953, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
    - 1954 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Mabel Randall, Letters to and from Randall Relating to Genealogical Research, 1929-1933 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Felicia Meyer Marsh (Timmy), Letters from Marsh, 1934-1945, undated; (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 18-21)
  - William Benton, 1939-1954; (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 22-26)
  - Project Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Treasury Department Art Projects, 1935-1938; (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 27-31)
    - U.S. Building at the New York World's Fair Awards, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Office of Civilian Defense Projects, 1941-1942 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - War Art Unit, 1943-1944; (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 34-35)
  - Greeting Cards, 1932-1951; (See also OV 12) (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Envelopes, 1922-1954; (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 37-40)
  - Oversize, Greeting Cards, 1932-1951; (See Box 2, F35) (Box OV 12)
- Diaries, 1912-1954; Series 3; (box 3; 1 linear foot)
  Series is comprised of Marsh's diaries, including ones that he kept for certain periods during his adolescence, ones that he kept to record his art work, and ones that he kept to record daily events and activities.
  Marsh's adolescent diaries date from 1912 to 1913 and from 1916. The 1912 diary is the most complete, with daily entries for the entire year. The 1913 and 1916 diaries are composed of almost daily entries for the months of January and February, but are blank for the remaining months of each year. Adolescent diaries primarily record Marsh's daily outdoor activities (such as skating, sledding, and coasting in the winter, and playing tennis and swimming in the summer) with friends including Lloyd Goodrich, the day's weather, his studies, illnesses, and outings to the theater (to see movies and vaudeville shows). Diaries also allude to his artistic activities, such as painting and drawing a weekly cartoon for The Nutley Bulletin, and include some illustrations and sketches.
  Marsh's art work diaries date from 1929 to 1933. Each diary consists of an "index" of the art work referred to therein, including title, date, and page numbers for relevant entries, and dated entries, comprising notes about the particular art work on which he worked that day. His notes typically include information about dimensions, methods and techniques used, time worked, what was drawn, and/or what prints were made. These diaries document the work he carried out, as well as the way in which he worked, on his paintings and prints during this time period. Similar notes for the time period from 1935 to 1944 can be found in the art notebooks.